Good morning today's דף daf *daf* is נ"ג *nun gimmel*. We pick
up at the top, very top, first line. We're talking we're finally
up to that moment that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol*
is in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim, *Kodesh Kodashim*. You know, he
has walked through the curtains, he's standing by the rock which we'll
find out of, or in the בית ראשון *Bayit Rishon* by the
קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim, *Kodesh Kodashim*. He puts the fire pan down.
He puts on the incense. I want to remind you that what
we did not discuss here, but which we dealt with earlier, was
the complicated process by which he got the incense from the, from
the ladle back into his hands. It actually was debated if you
remember whether we say that חופין וחוזר וחופין *chofin v'chozer v'chofin*. Did
he have to do it again from his hands? Of course, we
assume that he did. He somehow managed to get it back into
his hands and put it now on the, on the fire pan
and the house fills up, meaning the קודשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* fills
up with smoke and then he is going to leave. It also
occurred to me, and you know, maybe this is self-evident,
but things I find things that are self-evident are worth saying, that,
that, you know, I pointed out before that, how a lot of
the משניות *Mishnayot* sort of are like pulling out and pulling in.
Like you think they're going to finally get around to talking about,
about the עבודה avodah, *Avodah*. Then they pull out: oh, and the
rest of the year they used to do these lines, and so
on and so forth. Then they get to the next stage: we
did this last week, oh, and the rest of the year this
is how they would bring up all the stuff. And it occurred
to me that, you know, part of what's achieved that way in
terms of the drama of what we're reading is if you went
straight and just said here's what he did, it would like, it
would not feel, I think, as, you know, momentous as, like you
wouldn't appreciate the uniqueness and the, the auspicious nature of what he
was doing. So by constantly sort of giving us a larger context
and then pulling back in, we're like prepared now for this, you
know, for this very special moment which is just so unique in
terms of what normally would be done. So that's where we are
now and, and we are going to and we pick up on
the top of נ"ג עמוד א' *nun gimmel amud aleph*, taking a
look at this next stage as he is burn, burning, putting the
incense on the fire. And as we said, he starts near and
he moves, you know, and he moves forward. He
moves so that he does not burn, so that he does not
burn his arm. What? That's מחלוקת *machloket*, but that was what אביי
Abaye *Abaye* said makes sense. Okay, so let's take a look. I'm
trying to see if I can actually get this started. Okay, sorry,
buddy, just working once again trying to get this started. This spot.
Oh, I see.
Okay.
All righty. Okay, so תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*, our rabbis taught, top
again of first line נ"ג עמוד א' *nun gimmel amud aleph*. ונתן
את הקטרת על האש לפני ה' ve-natan et ha-ketoret al ha-esh lifnei
Hashem, *v'natan et haketoret al ha'esh lifne Hashem*, and you shall put
the קטרת ketoret *ketoret* on the fire before
God. לפני ה' lifnei Hashem *lifne Hashem*, when you are in the
presence of God, when you are in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim,
*Kodesh Kodashim*, do not put the קטרת ketoret, *ketoret* on the fire
pan outside and bring in. להוציא מליבן של צדוקים Tzedukim *lehotzi mi'liban
shel Tzedukim*, and this is like this proof, this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
uproots the approach of the, you know, disproves the approach of the
צדוקים Tzedukim *Tzedukim* שאומרים יתקן מבחוץ ויכניס *sheomrim yitaken mibachutz v'yachnis*, that
you first put the incense on the fire pan outside and you
bring it in after the incense is already burning, you come in
with the incense burning. And I will remind you that the, what
do you call it, I'll remind you that the,
they taught, you know, the whole period when they were teaching him
during the seven days about preparing the incense and they taught him
how to do it, right, they made him take this oath that
he would not do it like the way the צדוקים Tzaddukim. *Tzedukim*
do it. And a
lot of the assumption about why the כהן *Kohen* might die when
he's in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim, *Kodesh Kodashim* has to do
with these concerns about, you know, that he would do it like
the צדוקים Tzadokim *Tzedukim* did it and that would somehow lead to
his death. Okay, so now we are finally getting to, what do
you call it, to the fact about the פסוקים psukim? *psukim* in
which this debate is based. Okay, so let's take a look. מאי
דרוש *mai darosh*? What does it now, this is quite fascinating, right?
Let's hear what the צדוקים Tzadokim. *Tzedukim* held. So what, what did
the צדוקים *Tzedukim* say? מאי דרוש *mai darosh*? So, כי בענן אראה
על הכפורת ki be'anan eraeh al hakapporet, *ki b'anan eraeh al hakaporet*,
right? בזאת יבוא אהרן Aharon אל הקדש *b'zot yavo Aharon el hakodesh*
מבית לפרוכת mibeit laparochet. *mibeit laparochet*? What's the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? Hold
on. אחרי מות שני בני אהרן Acharei Mos shnei bnei Aharon, *achrei
mot shnei bnei Aharon* is that, is that the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*?
Is that the one where we started?
Oh. Hold on. אחרי
מות שני בני אהרן Acharei mos shnei bnei Aharon,
בקרבתם לפני ה' lifnei Hashem וימותו *achrei
mot shnei bnei Aharon b'korvatam lifne Hashem vayamutu*. Right, right. אחרי מות
שני בני אהרן
acharei
mos
shenei venei Aharon, בקרבתם לפני ה' lifnei Hashem. וימותו ויאמר ה' אל
משה Moshe, דבר אל אהרן Aharon, אחיך ואל יבוא בכל עת אל
הקדש מבית לפרוכת אל פני הכפורת אשר על הארון ולא ימות כי
בענן אראה על הכפורת v'lo yamut ki be'anan eraeh al hakapporet. *achrei
mot shnei bnei Aharon b'korvatam lifne Hashem vayamutu
vayomer Hashem el Moshe daber el Aharon achicha v'al yavo b'chol et
el hakodesh mibeit laparochet el pnei hakaporet asher al ha'aron v'lo yamut
ki b'anan eraeh al hakaporet*. So the כי בענן ki be-anan *ki
b'anan*, what ענן anan *anan* is it? Of course, פשט pshat *pshat*
is God always appears בתוך ענן anan *b'toch anan* and I, God,
my presence is myself על הכפורת al hakapporet *al hakaporet* in this
ענן anan. *anan* and therefore this is a very, you know, holy
place. The קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim. is a place where you directly
encounter God. That's where My cloud is, and therefore you need to
do all of this preparation. But interestingly, according to what we're about
to read, both חז"ל Chazal and the צדוקים understand that כי בענן
ki be-anan. does not refer to God's classic appearance בענן, be-anan, but
it refers to the ענן anan. of the קטורת, ketoret, the ענן
anan created by the burning of the קטורת. ketoret. So let's take
a look. Okay? So, כי בענן אראה על הכפרת. ki be-anan eraeh
al ha-kaporet.
מלמד, Melamed, so the צדוקים say, we teach, שתיקן... she-tiken... מלמד ש...
melamed she... I can't keep—I keep on losing my place because I'm
being
distracted. מלמד שיתקן מבחוץ ויכניס. Melamed she-yitaken mi-bachutz ve-yachnis. First have the
have the קטורת ketoret burning, then go in. So you appear when
you enter, אל יבא בכל עת, al yavo be-chol et, don't go
in at any time, כי בענן. ki be-anan If you want to
come in, it has to be with an ענן. anan You have
to enter in with an ענן. anan, So with an ענן anan,
I will see, you know, that's the way you enter בענן. be-anan.
That allows you to enter. That's how they read it. אמרו להם
חכמים, Amru lahem Chachamim, so the חכמים Chachamim said back, ולא כבר
נאמר, ve-lo kvar ne'emar, what do you mean? The פסוק pasuk says
very clearly, ונתן את הקטרת haketoret, על האש לפני ה', lifnei Hashem,
that it's put on the fire in the presence of God. So
how do you say—it clearly means you put it in when you're
in the קדש קדשים. kodesh kodashim אם כן מה תלמוד לומר כי
בענן אראה על הכפרת, im ken ma talmud lomar ki be-anan eraeh
al ha-kaporet, so what do we do with that verse? So rather
than, as I said, interpret the word ענן anan. just mean God's
presence in the ענן, anan, no, מלמד שנותן בה מעלה עשן. melamed
she-noten bah ma'aleh ashan. It does talk about, it means about the
קטורת. ketoret. But מלמד שנותן בה מעלה עשן, melamed she-noten bah ma'aleh
ashan, it means what you have to do is you have to
put one of the ingredients of the קטורת ketoret has to be
this herb of מעלה עשן. ma'aleh ashan. You might remember that herb
we discussed which made the קטורת ketoret go straight up like a
pole, right, as opposed to sort of, you know, scatter. Remember that
about how they wouldn't—they didn't want to teach the secret of how
they made the קטורת, ketoret, how they knew about this herb. So
כי בענן אראה ki be-anan eraeh means yes, when I when you
when I appear on the כפרת, kaporet, when you come in in
order to see Me, it has to be with an ענן, anan.
but it means make sure that the קטורת ketoret creates the ענן.
anan It doesn't mean that you enter in enveloped in an ענן,
anan right, it means make sure that when you encounter Me, it
is
through—it is the קטורת ketoret creating an ענן. anan Okay. But so
it's quite fascinating that they are willing to concede that the ענן
anan does refer to the קטורת. ketoret.
I'm sorry, I thought מעלה עשן ma'aleh ashan made it straight.
Yeah, I know. I was waiting for somebody to ask that. I
wondered about that too. You know, even without the מעלה עשן, ma'aleh
ashan, it would still make smoke, but it might puff out or
scatter out. Right. Well, that was the discussion before. That—so they did
not discuss how the ענן anan was, well, that's discussed whether it
would be quick or or take time in terms of whether it
would go straight or disperse, that the גמרא Gemara focused on this
מעלה עשן. ma'aleh ashan.
I thought the קטורת ketoret always a מעלה עשן, ma'aleh ashan, just
these people knew which kind made it go up straight.
I think the גמרא Gemara said that the name of the herb
was מעלה
עשן ma'aleh ashan actually, not that they—not that there was always... but
yes, but no, but with or without the herb, it would obviously
smoke, it would be smoke, which is why that's Michael's question and
I was wondering as well.
I assumed that for the קטורת ketoret there's always a smoke accelerator,
if you will, but not everybody knew the best one.
Right, that could be, that could be. You're you're translating מעלה עשן
ma'aleh ashan as a generic, like Frigidaire, right, or Band-Aid. Right. But
I think the גמרא Gemara had it more as a specific brand
name. But anyway, but yes, there would always be smoke. Oh, so
you want to revisit מעלה עשן ma'aleh ashan as make sure you
put in something, right, not necessarily the מעלה עשן, ma'aleh ashan, make
sure there's something that creates that smoke. That's a possible read, that's
a nice read. Okay. But they're willing to concede it does mean
you that that you need the ענן הקטרת anan ha-ketoret in order
to have this encounter, but it doesn't mean you enter in with
that ענן anan, already created.
Where do you get to?
Okay, well let's take a look.
So the ברייתא braita says like this. מלמד שנותן בה מעלה עשן.
Melamed she-noten bah ma'aleh ashan. ומנין שנותן בה מעלה עשן? U-minayin she-noten
bah ma'aleh ashan? Now, of course, this is a funny ברייתא, braita,
because right after saying that we learn from כי בענן ki be'anan,
that you need מעלה עשן, ma'aleh ashan, then it says that where
do we know you have to have מעלה עשן? ma'aleh ashan? שנאמר
וכסה ענן הקטרת את הכפרת. she-ne'emar ve-chisa anan ha-ketoret et ha-kaporet.
It's very clear from that פסוק pasuk that when you burn it,
the ענן anan created by the קטורת ketoret has to cover the
כפרת. kaporet. So therefore, clearly from that פסוק, pasuk you see that
that has to be done, that has to be happening when the
קטורת ketoret is burning, this ענן anan has to be created. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask in a minute, why did
you need to quote two פסוקים? psukim, You already—right, to say that
was what the first פסוק pasuk meant. But from these two פסוקים,
psukim, we see that yes, you have to create an ענן, anan
but it doesn't mean the ענן anan, is created outside, the ענן
anan is created inside. By the way, I did want to say,
הלא נתן בה מעלה עשן, halo natan bah ma'aleh ashan, so from
there we see that if you did not create—do the מעלה עשן,
ma'aleh ashan, או שחיסר אחת מכל סמניה, o she-chisar achat mi-kol samaneha,
or you were missing one of the ingredients of the fragrances of
the incense, חייב מיתה, chayav mita, you're deserving of death. And how
we know you're deserving of death, we'll get to in a minute,
like, you know, we sort of say the פיטום... pitum... like you
know we sort of say the פיטום הקטורת, Pitum HaKetoret, you know
on שבת, Shabbos, and we mention this שחיסר אחת מכל סממניה חייב
מיתה, shechisar achas mikol samimaneha chayav misa,
we'll talk about that in a minute. But before we do, I
just want to say one thing, which is that verse from later.
That verse, the later verse is probably what influences even חז"ל Chazal
to read the first verse of כי בענן, Ki BeAnan meaning הענן
הקטורת ha-anan ha-ketoret and not the ענן anan that normally appears, because
this early verse says כי בענן אראה על הכפורת, ki be'anan eraeh
al hakapporet. so here the keywords ענן, anan כפורת, kapporet, right? And
then later when it actually talks about him burning the incense, what
does it say? It says ונתת את הקטרת על האש לפני ה'
וכסה ענן הקטרת את הכפורת. v'natan et haketoret al ha-esh lifnei Hashem
v'chisa anan haketoret et hakapporet. ענן הקטרת את הכפורת. anan haketoret et
hakapporet. כי בענן אראה ki be'anan era'eh. על הכפורת. Al HaKaporet. So
it's not a, you know, it's a pretty reasonable read to say
the first ענן anan, when God appears על הכפורת is the same
as the later we hear that the ענן anan covers the...
but the other one is ענן הקטורת anan haketoret and this first
one isn't.
No, it doesn't say the word הקטרת, but still the juxtaposition of
ענן anan? and כפורת, kapporet, so that's why even חז"ל Chazal are
willing to concede that the first verse means ענן הקטורת, anan haketoret,
but they just say it doesn't mean you create it ahead of
time, it means that when you do it in the קודש קדשים,
Kodesh Kodashim make sure that it does fill with the... create an
ענן, anan, create a cloud and does fill the,
you know, go over the כפורת. kapporet. Yeah.
Where in the ברייתא braita have חז"ל Chazal proved that the קטרת
ketoret is burned inside and not outside?
No, that's from the פסוק pasuk ונתת את הקטרת על האש לפני
ה'. v'natan et haketoret al ha-esh lifnei Hashem. לפני ה' lifnei Hashem
means what is the presence of God? That is, now of course
it's funny because very often לפני ה' can mean, right, remember to
tell, remember to talk about taking the coals מלוא המחתה גחלי אש
מעל המזבח מלפני ה'. melo machtat gachalei esh me-al hamizbeach milifnei Hashem.
You know מלפני ה' milifnei Hashem can mean from the outside. Yeah,
maybe it means right here לפני ה'. But their argument is, wait
maybe they said that, their argument is that once you're in this
inside the היכל Heichal and it says לפני ה', that's got to
mean the most לפני ה' possible. That's how they read it, which
is a pretty reasonable read. Okay. So now let's continue. Okay, so
we have this חייב מיתה chayav misa which we'll get back to.
Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. ותיפוק ליה. v'teipuk lei. So this גמרא Gemara first jumps
right into this issue of חייב מיתה. chayav misa. ותיפוק ליה דקמיה
ביאה ריקנית. v'teipuk lei de-kamayeh biah reikanit. Why don't we learn out
that you're חייב מיתה chayav misa because you are entering in a
empty entering? What does that mean, an empty entering? So חז"ל Chazal
understand because the פסוק pasuk says ולא ימות. v'lo yamut. Right, the
פסוק pasuk says like this, the פסוק pasuk. says,
where is it, right there at the beginning?
It says אל
יבוא בכל עת אל הקודש מבית לפרוכת אל פני הכפורת
אשר על הארון ולא ימות. al
yavo be-chol et el hakodesh mibeit laparochet el p'nei hakapporet
asher al ha-aron v'lo yamut. ולא
ימות. v'lo yamut. Okay,
so what does ולא ימות v'lo yamut mean? So חז"ל Chazal understand
why would the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol when under what circumstances would
he be חייב מיתה? chayav misa? So it understands, it reads the
פסוק pasuk two ways. One is אל יבוא בכל עת ולא ימות.
al yavo be-chol et v'lo yamut. Don't just walk in סתם. stam.
That actually if somebody enters into the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim let's
say in the context of עבודה, avodah? and is enters in as
a ביאה ריקנית, biah reikanit, an empty entering, he's not in the
context of bringing קטרת, ketoret just סתם stam walks in, חייב מיתה.
chayav misa. אל יבוא בכל עת ולא ימות. al yavo be-chol et
v'lo yamut. You're not allowed to come in סתם stam and then
you're deserving of death which actually is, I would say פשט pshat
of the פסוקים, pesukim, without doing this whole procedure you're חייב מיתה.
chayav misa. Okay, you'll be deserving of death. You know now the
other reading is, right, why don't you do...
I'm sorry, you're saying don't go in to do an עבודה? avodah.
Don't go in unless you have something with you. But you go
in later to take out the...
Okay, but that's not ביאה ריקנית. biah reikanit. That's for a...
and this go in without anything, coming into a room... Don't go...
No, no, no, it doesn't mean without anything in your hand. Don't
go in purposeless for no purpose. Okay, ביאה ריקנית biah reikanit means
for no purpose. Or no licensed purpose, no justified purpose.
Or no licensed purpose related to the עבודה. avodah Like if you
don't have either a, you know, a trade purpose or an עבודה
avoda purpose.
Exactly, exactly. Right, right, right. So exactly, don't go in without any
justified and authorized purpose. Okay, any unauthorized entry. Okay, but not just
unauthorized because it's not like you're... it's just ביאה ריקנית biah reikanit
is purposeless, any purposeless entry. Okay, so the other way to read
the verse though is that the, the line before that if it's
לא נתן במעלה עשן או שחיסר אחת מכל סממניה lo natan b'maaleh
ashan o shechisar achas mikol samimaneha emphasizes not the אל יבוא בכל
עת, al yavo be-chol et, but emphasizes ולא ימות כי בענן v'lo
yamut ki be'anan. אראה eira'eh על הכפורת. Don't, you will not be
deserving of death because I can only be seen בענן. be'anan. I
can only be seen if you bring the קטרת ketoret in the
right way. So if the קטרת ketoret is not the completely correct
קטרת ketoret or it doesn't have the ענן anan then that's also
ולא ימות כי בענן. velo yamut ki be-anan. So the גמרא's Gemara
question is, okay, but that's saying the same thing. You're saying don't
come in unless you're burning the קטרת ktoret properly. Why do I
need to say you're חייב מיתה chayav misa for burning the קטרת
ktoret improperly, say you're חייב מיתה chayav misa because you did not,
in the end you didn't do... Right עבודה avodah and therefore it
was a ביאה ריקנית. bi'ah reikanit. Where would there be a gap
between those two formulations? So let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון ששוגג בביאה,
kegon sheshogeg be'bi'ah, והזיד בהקטרה. ve'hizid behaktara.
So you're only חייב מיתה chayav misa if you do it במזיד,
bemezid, again, not that the court will put you to death, but
מיתה בידי שמים. misa bidei shamayim. So
if you do this עבירה, aveira, either ביאה ריקנית bi'ah reikanit or
burning the קטורת ketoret incorrectly. So רב ששת Rav Sheshet basically says,
look, you're right. Those two can always overlap, okay? But there could
be if you knew about one and not the other, if we
can't get you for A, we'll get you for B. So if
you were שוגג shogeg and you didn't know it was אסור assur
to enter in a ביאה ריקנית, bi'ah reikanit, but you knew it
was אסור assur to burn the incorrect קטורת ketoret or it was
אסור assur to burn the קטורת ketoret without the מעלה עשן, ma'aleh
ashan, then even though we can't get you חייב מיתה chayav misa
for ביאה ריקנית, bi'ah reikanit, we'll get you חייב מיתה chayav misa
for burning the קטורת ketoret incorrectly. So what he's basically saying is
fine, I'm not going to be, I'm not interested in finding a
case where you'll have one scenario without the other. Let's concede that
basically you'll always get both you know, whenever you have the burning
of the קטורת ketoret incorrectly, you're also going to have, meaning you
can have a ביאה ריקנית bi'ah reikanit without the incorrect burning, you
just walk in. But whenever you have the incorrect burning, it also
is a ביאה ריקנית. bi'ah reikanit. I'll concede that. But I still
want to say you're חייב chayav for the incorrect burning because you
might not be חייב chayav for the ביאה ריקנית bi'ah reikanit just
because you were שוגג. shogeg. So I'm pointing out that you're also
going to have a חיוב מיתה chiyuv misa for the burning incorrectly
and that's what you'd be חייב chayav for. Yes, רבקה?
Rivka? Only גדול Gadol does the קטורת? ketoret? Another family does it,
right? Oh, he does it? Correct, correct. So why
should
he
be חייב מיתה?
chayav misa?
That's a good point. If he knows, if he doesn't know what
he's doing is wrong, then he's an אונס. onus. He's not just
a שוגג, shogeg, he's an אונס, onus, you're absolutely correct. You're absolutely
correct. So you're right, the only חיוב מיתה chiyuv misa would be
if he was aware that what he was doing was not only
was he aware that it was prohibited, but he was aware that
what he was doing was actually the wrong קטורת. ketoret. That's an
excellent point, you're absolutely right about that. So that would be the
scenario.
The same structure of thinking as the ברייתא braita שבת, Shabbat, he
knew it was שבת Shabbat but didn't know the מלאכה melakha was
אסור?
assur? Yeah, exactly. You have to know both, right. Okay. So רב
אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, אפילו תימא הזיד בזו ובזו. afilu teima
hizid bazu uvzu. No,
רב אשי Rav Ashi says, I'm going to look for a more
interesting case. He knows it's אסור assur to enter a ביאה ריקנית,
bi'ah reikanit, he knows it's אסור assur to burn the קטורת ketoret
incorrectly, he's willingly violating both, and nevertheless, it's possible to burn the
קטורת ketoret incorrectly without having a ביאה ריקנית. bi'ah reikanit. How could
you do that? כגון דעייל שתי הקטרות. kegon de'ayeil shtei haktarot. This
really sounds like a... like almost אחרוניש. achronish. He brings in two
הקטרות, haktarot, okay? אחת שלמה ואחת חסרה. achat shleima ve'achat chasera. One
is correct and one is lacking. One is full, one doesn't have
all of the ingredients or doesn't have the מעלה עשן. ma'aleh ashan.
And he's going to burn two קטורות ketorot while he's there, okay?
So אביאה לא מחייב, abi'ah lo mechayev, he's not חייב chayav for
the purposeless entering, he's doing this at the same time, you understand.
דהא עייל שלמה, de'ha ayeil shleima, because he's doing a legitimate entry
when he goes and he brings both in. He burns the correct
one, so that justifies his entry. So his entry was now justified.
But אהקטרה מחייב, ahaktara mechayev, now that he's done
that, he can't leave well enough alone. He's got to now burn
the second one. The second one is the one that's not a
full קטורת. ketoret. That now יחייב מיתה yechayev misa for the הקטרה,
haktara, דקמקטיר קטורת חסרה de'kamaktir ketoret chasera because you're burning a lacking
קטורת. ketoret. So your whole entry was legitimate, but you should have
stopped while you were ahead. You went and you burned the second
one, for that you're going to be חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Okay,
I just have to say it totally reminds me of that joke
about the two bombs on the plane, which I tell you often.
Do
you know the joke? The guy's the actuary, and he's always so
nervous going on a plane because he's figured out the odds that
there's going to be a bomb on a plane, and he's like
always and he's like the whole flight he's miserable. So once he's
on a flight with his friend, and he's like completely calm. Says,
how come you're so calm? I thought you know, you're always afraid
of the odds of a bomb on the plane. Says, yeah, he
says, but now I beat the system. I brought a bomb on
the plane. What are the chances of there being two bombs?
So this guy says, I brought two קטורות! ketorot! Oh! Yes, the...
the...
yes, what did you say about this argument? If it were two
פרושים prushim having this argument it would be perfectly legit. Right.
Oh wait, this discussion about... about ביאה ריקנית bi'ah reikanit and הקטרה
שלמה haktara shleima is not the צדוקים.
No, no, I understand.
The earlier argument. Yes, right. Yeah, that's the thing. The גמרא Gemara
presents it as a completely reasonable interpretation of the פסוקים, psukim but
somehow there's a consensus that it's wrong. Well, I mean, it's very
obvious, I was looking at it again. It says ולקח מלא
המחתה גחלי
אש מעל המזבח מלפני ה׳ ומלא חפניו קטורת סמים דקה והביא מבית
לפרוכת.
ve'lakach melo hamachta gachalei esh me'al hamizbe'ach milifnei Hashem u'melo
chofnav
ketoret samim daka ve'heivi mibeit laparochet. Then ונתן את הקטורת על
האש לפני ה׳.
ve'natan
et
haketoret al ha'esh lifnei Hashem. That's
a good point. It's not just מבית לפרוכת. Right, they would mean
ונתנה, ve'natana, and you had already placed. You know, but you're right,
you're... Right, so that's right. Okay, exactly.
And they point out that's not the... divide there and so this
is not just.
So that's an interesting question. Do you think that there was like
a profound theological issue about what you know like this idea of
like why can't be you could understand that like can you directly
approach Hashem you know do you need to always be doing it
through a cloud that you're enveloped by the cloud when you enter
in? You know you could understand it theologically but I didn't you
didn't mean that when you said an ideological divide did you?
No I meant to I meant so they are reform. Right you
can't argue with that. Right right it becomes it just
it becomes identified as a position that's חוץ למחנה. chutz l'machaneh. I
also think what's what's worth pointing out is and it's similar to
like we had a similar very profound issue which is you know
about the about the ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim like the צדוקים didn't
believe in the ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim that you know as we
know from Josephus many of the כהנים kohanim were צדוקים. And therefore
and as we know from reading the גמרא Gemara חז"ל Chazal you
know would like to see it as if the rabbis were the
ones in control of how things were done in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. That there was a בית דין Beis Din that the
כהנים kohanim would always check with and ultimately חז"ל Chazal oversaw it.
So I certainly see a lot of this as sort of a
question of like who's who's the authority here you know is it
Tzadokim way of doing things or the or the rabbinic way of
doing things? So I think that that's also part of it you
know and that therefore the issues about these very focal עבודות avodot
you know of you know that are major public עבודות avodot I
mean even though this is private but you know this very day
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur becomes this major you know issue of
a struggle for you know for authority. That's partly how I see
it yes Charlie. Okay so let's take a look. So back though
to this question about the the two types of prohibitions the entering
in the empty entering and the and the incorrect burning of the
קטורת. ktoret. Okay אמר מר. Amar Mar. So now going back to
what the ברייתא braita said. ומנין שנותן בה מעלה עשן. U'minayin shenotan
bah ma'aleh ashan. So after the rabbis said that the פסוק pasuk?
of כי בענן ki be'anan, meant that you have to put some
מעלה עשן ma'aleh ashan in to create the smoke then they quote
again a פסוק. pasuk תלמוד לומר וכסה ענן הקטורת את הכפורת. Talmud
lomar v'chisa anan haktoret es hakaporet. That when you're burning it the
the cloud has to envelop. So the גמרא Gemara says קרא בי
קרא? Kra bi kra? You need a פסוק pasuk. to prove a
פסוק? pasuk It's a great way of saying it you know you
already quoted a פסוק pasuk you said how do I know it's
doing it and you quote another פסוק. pasuk So you need a
פסוק pasuk to prove a פסוק pasuk קרא בי קרא? kra bi
kra? So אמר רב יוסף הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Yosef hachi ka'amar.
Here's what the ברייתא braita means. אין לי אלא עלה מעלה עשן.
Ein li ela aleh ma'aleh ashan.
I only know that that you that we that you're required or
that you're that it's that's it's that it's acceptable to do the
leaf from the מעלה עשן. ma'aleh ashan. Again now we're talking about
a specific plant called the מעלה עשן. ma'aleh ashan.
עיקר מעלה עשן מנין? Ikar ma'aleh ashan minayin? How do I know
you can even use the root of the מעלה עשן? ma'aleh ashan?
So תלמוד לומר וכסה Talmud lomar v'chisa which meaning somehow that extra
פסוק pasuk you know it's so funny does וכסה v'chisa mean restrictive
or is it mean more inclusive? Often we say if it's being
repeated it's being more restrictive. But here it's read somehow reading like
וכסה מכל מקום v'chisa mikol makom that even if you use the
less powerful part of the plant and maybe it doesn't create as
much smoke as would be ideal as long as you got the
smoke and it covers the כפורת kaporet that's sufficient. So that's what
we learn out from the second
פסוק pasuk of a broader category of what you can use to
create the smoke. So אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye so Abaye
said that
והאיפכא תניא? v'ha'ipcha tanya? But the ברייתא braita teaches opposite? That the
עיקר ikar is better than the the root is better than the
leaf. Why where's the ברייתא braita teach? דתניא נתן בעיקר מעלה עשן
D'tanya natan b'ikar ma'aleh ashan if you put the root of the
plant in it היה מתמר ועולה כמקל. haya mitamer v'oleh kemakel. That's
when it would go up straight like a pole. עד שמגיע לשמי
קורה Ad shemagia lishmei kora till it got to be like a
you know to the beams of the roof. כיון שהגיע לשמי קורה
Keivan shehigia lishmei kora once it hit the beams of the roof
ממשמש ויורד memashmesh v'yored it would sort of it's a very interesting
verb it would feel its way down and come down בכותלים bakotalim
on the walls until meaning like it would hit that you know
straight up spread out on the roof and then creep down creep
down excellent creep down the walls okay creep down the walls. עד
שנתמלא הבית עשן Ad shenitmaleh habayit ashan until it was filled with
smoke שנאמר והבית ימלא עשן Shene'emar v'habayit yimalei ashan and
from ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. So therefore anyway you see that the root would
be the better one. אלא אמר אביי הכי קאמר Ela amar Abaye
hachi ka'amar fine so reverse it. אין לי אלא עיקר מעלה עשן.
Ein li ela ikar ma'aleh ashan. I only know it's good if
you use the root from the plant. עלה מעלה עשן Aleh ma'aleh
ashan if you use the leaf from the plant מנין? minayin? תלמוד
לומר וכסה. Talmud lomar v'chisa. The extra וכסה v'chisa is coming to
tell you even a more you know even the less ideal part
of the plant. רב ששת אמר. Rav Sheshet amar. Now that's one
read of why we need two פסוקים psukim about the cloud covering
it.
Okay. That is one of these stretches again. Right.
רב ששת אמר אין לי אלא אוהל מועד. Rav Sheshet amar ein
li ela Ohel Moed. רב ששת Rav Sheshet says no you need
the two פסוקים psukim to tell you the following. I only know
that you're obligated to do this in אוהל מועד Ohel Moed right
because the whole emphasis of the פסוקים pesukim is וכן יעשה לאוהל
מועד השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם. V'chein ya'aseh l'Ohel Moed hashochein itam b'toch
tumatam. It's all about the אוהל מועד. Ohel Moed. How do I
know know it's a similar עבודה avodah by the by the מקדש,
Mikdash, and normally like we don't need a פסוק pasuk to tell
me if you bring the עולה olah the same way in the
מקדש Mikdash as you do in the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, and
you bring a חטאת chatas and you bring whatever. But here again,
I want to remind you that so much of the תורה's Torah
description of the purpose of the עבודה avodah is to cleanse the
מקדש, Mikdash, right, וכפר את הקדש מטמאת בני ישראל. v'chiper es hakodesh
mitumos bnei Yisrael.
So if it's about cleansing the מקדש, Mikdash, maybe there's a difference
between a portable מקדש Mikdash and a permanent מקדש, Mikdash, and maybe
there's a difference between אהל מועד Ohel Moed and the מקדש. Mikdash.
Now this is מן min אחרי מות Acharei Mos שני בני אהרן,
Bnei Aharon this is ongoing, and this is definitely אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. Right, right, but it doesn't say מנין לא אהרן, minayin
lo Aharon, מנין אין אהל מועד. minayin ain Ohel Moed. Okay, so
how do you know, so where were we, אין אלא אהל שבמדבר,
ain elo Ohel shebamidbar, שילה בית עולמים מנין? Shilo Beis Olamim minayin?
How do I know when we start, when it gets into ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and when you have the מקדש Mikdash of שילה
Shilo or you have the permanent house on the הר הבית, Har
HaBayis, how do I know that you similarly have the same? Now
he's not just saying the whole עבודה avodah is the same, how
do I know specifically the idea of the ענן הקטרת anan haktoret
is the same, that it has to cover, fill, create this whole
ענן? anan תלמוד לומר וכסה. Talmud lomar v'chisa. The extra, the repeating
of וכסה v'chisa is to tell you you have to do the
same עבודה avodah. with the קטרת ktoret whether you're in the אהל
מועד, Ohel Moed, whether you're in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
the גמרא Gemara says, האי וכן יעשה לאהל מועד השוכן אתם בתוך
טמאתם, hai v'chein ya'aseh l'Ohel Moed hashochein itam b'toch tumatam, no no
no, we get that from the פסוק pasuk says so shall you
do for אהל מועד Ohel Moed and the extra two words that
says השוכן אתם בתוך טמאתם hashochein itam b'toch tumatam
that I God dwell in your midst amongst your טומאה tumah means
wherever I God dwell, they understand that that word השוכן hashochein wherever
I make my my presence to dwell, that's where you do this
עבודה. avodah. So that tells you it's the same whether it's אהל
מועד Ohel Moed or whether it's the מקדש. Mikdash. So you don't
need a this extra פסוק וכסה. pasuk v'chisa. So אלא הכי קאמר.
ela hacha kamar. Okay fine, let's try again. אין אלא ביום הכיפורים,
ain ela b'Yom HaKippurim, I only know this requirement is on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. בשאר ימי השנה מנין? b'sha'ar yemoi hashana minayin? How
do I know in the rest of the year? תלמוד לומר וכסה.
talmud lomar v'chisa. The extra verse. Now what's the rest of the
year? What, if somebody just walks in the קדש קדשים kodesh kodashim
the rest of the year then this is how he has to
do it? Yeah. So it could be like the גר"א Gra says,
that well that's what the גר"א Gra says, that the פסוקים pesukim
are not only talking about what you do on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur but was also telling אהרן Aharon in general when he wanted
to enter in any time in the year that he could do
this עבודה. avodah. But no, the simple sense and it's going to
be supported later is we're also talking about requirements for the burning
of the קטרת ktoret that you did every single day twice a
day out here. So that wouldn't be a ביאת קדש bi'as kodesh
issue, but the burning of that you would do out here twice
a day, that still has the requirements of מעלה עשן malei ashan
and וחיסר אחת מכל סמניה, v'chissah achas mikol smaneha, right? We say
this every שבת, Shabbos, right, in the פיטום הקטרת, Pittum HaKtoret, וחיסר
אחת מכל סמניה חייב מיתה. chissah achas mikol smaneha chayav misa. So
we're not just talking about in here. So where it says ולא
ימות כי בענן אראה על הכפרת v'lo yamut ki be'anan era'eh al
hakaporeth that you're חייב מיתה chayav misa unless you do it properly,
that's understood to be applied even to the daily קטרת ktoret that
was burnt. And it has to be the full ingredients and it
has to be with כי בענן, ki be-anan. it has to create
this ענן, anan and if not you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Now
that is quite fascinating because we are always assuming, I'm always assuming,
right, that the whole idea כי בענן אראה על הכפרת ki be'anan
era'eh al hakaporeth and they even say that means the ענן הקטרת
anan haktoret that the emphasis of the מעלה עשן malei ashan is
about the is about יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But if you remember
right the discussion that they had about the family that knew how
to create the קטרת ktoret and the special thing that they knew
was this ingredient of the מעלה עשן, malei ashan, that was talking
about with the קטרת ktoret that they created for every single day,
right, that they would create the daily קטרת ktoret. and one of
the important things was the מעלה עשן. malei ashan. So it's quite
interesting that חז"ל Chazal take this whole idea of God's presence in
the ענן anan and creating this ענן הקטרת anan haktoret as a
way of at when you enter into the קדש kodesh. קדשים and
say that that is really required on a daily basis and if
you do that wrong even on a daily basis it's חייב מיתה.
chayav misa. So it raises I think an interesting question about this
question always comes up like what is the purpose of the קטרת
ktoret that you do daily? What's the purpose of it on יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur? יום כיפור Yom Kippur I think okay the גמרא
Gemara says
קטרת מכפר ktoret mechaper but I think as as we've been saying
the clearer sense of the focus of it is creating that allowing
somehow for that encounter with God and the even the ambiguity of
כי בענן אראה. ki be-anan erae, Is it God appears in God's
ענן anan or is he appearing in the ענן anan once we've
created the ענן anan. then that God will appear? But this somehow
allows for that encounter. I don't know if we would have said
the same about the daily קטרת. ketores, You don't have the sense
that the daily קטרת ketores is to create this type of encounter.
But somehow we're finding out that the same requirements with the same
חיוב מיתה chiyuv misa that apply in there and that sense of
the ענן anan. that allows for that encounter is required on a
daily basis. So I think that that's a fascinating idea that is
somehow on a daily basis even if it's not the same intensity
we're still trying to if you would sort of like model after
mimic. Somehow, you know, it has some attempt at a similar encounter
or some shadow of a similar encounter even on a daily basis,
which I think is very powerful. Yes, Michael.
I think that basically one is... I still find it a little
difficult because we say מיתה misah but the rest of it... ואראה
על הכפורת אשר על העדות. ve'erae al hakaporeis asher al ha'edus.
I understand. Well, that's what... that's my point. I think that's very
powerful that we're taking these פסוקים pesukim? that are about this day
and the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim and we're saying, oh, this teaches
me general קטורת. ketoret.
The hermeneutic of trying to do that as a...
of the פנימיות. penimiyut. Yeah, it's repetitive. It's the same עניין inyan
for יום כיפור Yom Kippur and קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim to the
same עניין inyan for כל ימות השנה kol yemos hashanah for the
היכל.
Heichal. Right, but what I'm also saying is that, you know, there
has to be... maybe I'm abstracting too much, but there's also an
element of the human endeavor and appreciating the Divine, that we have
to be the ענן anan. versus relying on God to be the
ענן. anan, Okay, I mean that's what it's trying to say, that
in other words it's not just God appearing in, you know...
you're just saying the פשט pshat of the כי בענן.
ki be-anan No, I'm saying like what... what's motivating us to say
that we... that we have to do something, meaning that in order
to really fully experience the Divine there has to be...
no, but I appreciate that. Yeah.
Not so clear that God only appears or encounters us as ענן.
anan There are plenty of
counter-examples.
God is always... כבוד השם נראה בענן. kevod Hashem ne'erah be-anan.
Yeah, but could maybe that's only in a public sense, that God
appears to people, to the אבות, Avos, to משה, Moshe to even
the נביאים, nevi'im, you know, there's no ענן.
anan, Right, right, but ואראה על הכפורת, ve'erae al hakaporeis, when it
speaks about ואראה על הכפורת, ve'erae al hakaporeis, it always speaks about
the ענן, anan, you know, right? That's how שמות Shemos ends, right?
That the ענן anan. fills the house and, you know, and לא
יוכל. lo yuchal.
Yeah, but that's in a public sense and you'd want... one would
have to figure out when was the ענן, anan הר סיני, Har
Sinai, the desert.
But you're also trying to explain why we're choosing to read כי
בענן ki be-anan as ענן הקטורת. anan haketoret.
You'd have to also check, God appears privately, speaks...
Jonathan, you had a point?
When was the קטורת ketoret offered in the sequence of days, was
it with the תמיד? tamid?
Yeah, yeah, it was during the process of the תמיד. tamid.
With the תמיד? tamid?
Also, same time, but a little later. Right?
I mean, you forget, they did... I forget the exact order, it
was a whole דף or two, but, you know, you שחט shacht
it and then between the blood and the this, then you come
in and you do the מנורה menorah and the קטורת, ketoret, and
then this, and then you do the חביתין chavitin and that's when
you bring up the limbs, etc. Okay, let's go back. So now
we have it being done every day modeled after this. And with
the same consequences.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רב אשי Rav Ashi says, why do you need two פסוקים? psukim
חד למצוה וחד לעכב. chad lemitzvah vechad le'akeiv. Simple. One would have
just said you're required to do it, but maybe if you didn't
do it this way with the ענן, anan with the... you would
בדיעבד bedi'eved be okay. And the second time tells you no, even
בדיעבד bedi'eved it's required. Now תוספות Tosafos says, what? I don't get
it, תוספות Tosafos says. That's true by everything about יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. It says חוק chok and everything is מעכב. me'akeiv. תוספות Tosafos
says, well maybe it also means שאר ימות השנה, shear yemos hashanah,
that they're both... that you needed to say it twice to be
מעכב. me'akeiv. רבא Rava said: חד לעונש וחד לאזהרה. chad le'onash vechad
le'azhara. Now one פסוק pasuk is to tell you you're חייב מיתה.
chayav misah. The other פסוק pasuk, is to tell you you're prohibited
from doing it any other way. אל יבא כי בענן אראה. al
yavo ki be-anan erae. Don't come without doing it this way. And
the other פסוק pasuk says וכסה ענן הקטורת vechisa anan haketoret tells
you what you... you know, the... ולא ימות, velo yamut, you know.
So one says that if you don't do it this way, you
won't die, and the other says you're prohibited from doing it any
other way. תניא, Tanya, we learn in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says: ולא ימות, velo yamut, עונש, onash, right? So... כי
בענן אראה, ki be-anan erae, אזהרה. azhara. So the פסוק pasuk says,
right, it says בזאת יבא, bezos yavo, what is it? ואל יבא
בכל עת אל הקדש מבית לפרכת אשר על הארן ולא ימות. ve'al
yavo bechol es el hakodesh mibeis laparoches asher al ha'aron velo yamut.
So that would be the consequence, you'll die. כי בענן אראה, ki
be-anan era'eh that's telling you don't do it otherwise. Now כי בענן
ki be-anan. is not saying don't, but it connects with the ואל
יבא כי בענן. ve'al yavo ki be-anan. Do not enter except with
the ענן. anan So the ואל יבא כי בענן ve'al yavo ki
be-anan is your prohibition, ולא ימות velo yamut is the consequence. Okay.
So... now, ולא ימות velo yamuss,
כי בענן. Ki Be'anan יכול יהיו שניהם אמורים קודם מיתת בני אהרן?
yachol yiheyu shnehem amurim kodem misas bnei Aharon? Maybe it... maybe
both of these, the prohibition and the consequence, were told to משה
Moshe and אהרן, Aharon I guess, before אהרן's Aharon sons died. The
importance about this being, this ברייתא braisa is really exploring a little
bit the juxtaposition
of אחרי מות שני בני אהרן, Bnei Aharon right? They died, we
know what they did is that they brought קטורת, ketoret, right? They
brought אש זרה לפני השם, esh zarah lifnei Hashem, fire, you know,
you know, וישימו עליה קטורת, vayashimu aleha ketoret, right? וישימו עליה קטורת,
vayashimu aleha ketoret, right? Am I right? They say they burnt קטורת?
ketoret?
Somebody help
my... my mind. It
says... it says... איש מחתתו ויתנו בהן אש וישימו עליה קטורת. ish
machtaso vayisnu vahen esh vayashimu aleha ketoret. Okay. Of course, right afterwards,
it says, it... we have the prohibition about יין ושכר אל תשת,
yayin veshichar al tesht, which certainly leads to the possibility that they
were drunk when they were doing it. Okay, but also... And we
have, here it says אל יבוא בכל עת כי בענן אראה על
הכפרת, al yavo bechol eis ki be-anan era'eh al hakaporeth, and if
it means ענן הקטרת, anan haketores, and they did a קטרת, ketores
so it seems to suggest that what they did somehow was a
קטרת but they did it wrong. So maybe the explanation is that
they were already told before they died, this is how you have
to bring the קטרת if you're going inside the קדש הקדשים, kodesh
hakodashim, and that's why they were deserving of death because they were
given their marching orders and they were given their consequence and they
violated it. It wouldn't be fair that they were punished if they
were not told. So maybe this whole thing was said before they
died. Okay, and that would explain, well, and that would explain why
they died. So one minute, so let's see what it says. It
says, יכול יהיו שניהם אמורים קודם מיתת בני אהרן, yachol yiheyu shneihem
amurim kodem misas bnei aharon,
both the prohibition and the consequence. תלמוד לומר אחרי מות שני בני
אהרן. talmud lomar acharei mos shnei bnei aharon. No,
he was only told it after they died. יכול יהיו שניהם אמורים
אחר מיתת שני בני אהרן, yachol yiheyu shneihem amurim achar misas shnei
bnei aharon,
maybe both the prohibition and the consequence were said after they died
and none of this was hinted to beforehand. תלמוד לומר כי בענן
אראה על הכפרת talmud lomar ki be-anan era'eh al hakaporeth
because I will appear on the כפרת. kaporeth. Now where, what's the
proof? So רש"י Rashi says the proof is the לשון lashon עתיד.
asid. I will, or the גמרא's Gemara's actually I think going to
say. Yeah, the גמרא's Gemara's going to say. So, I will appear
in the future but I have yet to appear. Well, you know
when אהרן and his, when אהרן and children brought it, that was
ביום השמיני, beyom hashmini, that was the day that the משכן Mishkan
was erected, that was the day that God's ענן anan, filled the
משכן. Mishkan. So what do you mean I will in the future
appear? You already appeared on the day that the משכן Mishkan was
erected. So it must be that this was said before they died,
before the משכן Mishkan was erected.
But you said a second ago that it wasn't.
I, hold on a second. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? So how do
you reconcile this? אזהרה קודם מיתה, azharah kodem misah, ah, they were
warned before they died and therefore as the gad said I will
in the future, that was said before that part of the פרשה
parsha was said before the ביום השמיני, beyom hashmini, before it was
erected.
That פרשה parsha is from elsewhere.
I understand, but עונש, onesh, but the consequence ולא ימות, that was
אחר מיתה achar misah after they died. Now again it's chopping up
a פסוק, pasuk it's very bizarre. מאי תלמודא? mai talmuda? Where, what's
the idea that כי בענן אראה ki be-anan era'eh, means that it
was said earlier? אמר רבא אמר קרא כי בענן אראה amar Rava
amar kra ki be-anan era'eh I will appear ועדיין לא נראה v'adayin
lo nireh and I have not yet appeared. So that part of
the פסוק pasuk, had to be said before ביום השמיני. beyom hashmini.
Now I do want to point out two things about this. Okay,
A, besides that it's grappling with the juxtaposition of מיתת בני אהרן
misas bnei aharon and you know, but it's forced to say they
couldn't have known about this ahead of time, so stuff split it
up, but it has now said that ענן anan means the ענן
anan that God normally appears in, not ענן הקטרת. anan haketores. כי
בענן be-anan, אראה, right,
is not when I appear on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and you
bring it, then you have to create this ענן, anan then it
would be future. It's about on a future יום כיפור Yom Kippur
or on a future day when you do this עבודה. avodah No,
now we're saying the ענן anan. means God's regular ענן anan where
God appears and then the גמרא Gemara says, well that already happened,
you know, way back in ביום השמיני. beyom hashmini. So what do
you mean the future? So ענן anan now is being interpreted more,
I would say, the, you know, like what maybe the first assumption
would be, which would be God's normal appearance by ענן. anan The
other thing that is interesting is that when it says about the
ענן anan filling the, filling the משכן Mishkan on ביום השמיני, beyom
hashmini,
let's see what it says. It says,
so they did the whole thing on ביום השמיני. beyom hashmini. וישא
אהרן את ידיו אל העם ויברכם וירד מעשות החטאת והעלה והשלמים ויבא
משה ואהרן אל אהל מועד ויצאו ויברכו את העם וירא כבוד ה'
אל כל העם. vayissa Aharon es yadav el ha-am vayivarkhem vayered me-assos
hachattas ve-ha'olah vehashelamim vayavo Moshe v'Aharon el ohel moed vayetzu vayivarkhu es
ha-am vayera khvod Hashem el kol ha-am. ותצא אש מלפני ה' vatesse
eish milifnei Hashem and they fell on their faces and ויקחו
בני אהרן. vayikchu bnei Aharon. So the only thing it says is
כבוד ה' khvod Hashem was seen to everybody. So even if it's
כבוד ה' khvod Hashem seen בענן, be-anan which how it normally appears,
it wasn't על הכפרת, al hakaporeth, it wasn't God's intense presence filling
the כפרת, kaporeth, right? So again it's quite fascinating the interpretation of
this verse, כי בענן אראה על הכפרת, ki be-anan era'eh al hakaporeth,
A, where we're finally saying ענן anan means the normal ענן anan,
that God appears, but B, we're saying that already took place at
the time of ביום השמיני, beyom hashmini, the time of the erection
of the משכן. Mishkan. You didn't hear the emphasis of the כפרת.
kaporeth. I would even tell you at the end of שמות Shemos
where it does talk about God's presence filling the משכן Mishkan and
that really is a important פסוקים psukim to read as they relate
to this idea of כי בענן. Listen to the פסוקים psukim. that
end ספר שמות. Sefer Shemos. ויכס הענן את אהל מועד וכבוד ה'
מלא את המשכן ולא יכול משה לבוא אל אהל מועד כי שכן
עליו הענן וכבוד ה' מלא את המשכן ובהעלות הענן מעל המשכן יסעו
בני ישראל בכל מסעיהם ואם לא יעלה הענן ולא יסעו עד יום
העלותו. vayakhas he-anan es ohel moed ukhvod Hashem malei es ha-Mishkan v'lo
yakhol Moshe lavo el ohel moed ki shakhan alav he-anan ukhvod Hashem
malei es ha-Mishkan uve-he'alos he-anan me'al ha-Mishkan yis'u bnei Yisrael bekhol maseihem
ve'im lo ya'aleh he-anan v'lo yis'u ad yom he-alosso.
So God's presence fills, the ענן of God's presence fills the משכן
Mishkan and משה Moshe. can't even enter. But you know what's important
to note? It's the whole משכן, Mishkan, it's not just the קדש
הקדשים. kodesh hakodashim. So to be thinking about this issue, God sometimes
appears בענן outside the משכן. Mishkan. Sometimes you have the sense that
God's entire presence fills the משכן Mishkan with the ענן but the
entire משכן. Mishkan. And here it's specifically about the קדש. And על
הכפורת. So the fact that the גמרא Gemara took this פסוק pasuk,
of כי בענן and A, said it's talking about the normal ענן,
and B, related it to יום השמיני, Yom HaShemini, which it wasn't
emphasizing the משכן Mishkan and the כפורת, Kaporet, is quite fascinating. But
because it does that, it splits up when this event here when
this verse was given and to what degree בני אהרן Bnei Aharon
knew of this problem before they did what they did. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues. So ואלא מאי טעמא איענוש? ve'ela mai ta'ama
i'anush? So again, fascinating. It assumes that they would not have been
punished, they would not have gotten this death had they not been
not only prohibited, which now it's saying they were, but forewarned about
the consequence, which is not פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim You
know, פשט of the פסוקים psukim is that God's presence is so,
you know, so powerful. Somebody sort of explained it like a metaphor,
like like like you know, an electricity, you
know high voltage electricity generator. Like you know just so much power
there that it gives life to everything but if you get too
close without knowing, being the right precautions, you're going to get zapped.
Okay? And you see that, right? You know when the ארון aron
slips off of the עגלה, agala, right? and you know and עזא
Uzah tries to capture it, boom, gets you know he dies, you
know? So that's the whole thing. There's this power and this danger
and you have to take the right precaution. It's not just oh
you it's not this legalistic sense of you were warned and you
knew the consequences and you did it במזיד be'meizid and therefore you're
going to get the deserved punishment. You know, that's not the sense
you get in the פסוקים psukim about why this death like the
death of בני אהרן occurred. But חז"ל Chazal have like legalized it,
halachized it, and therefore they could not have gotten their punishment had
they not been not only prohibited but forewarned of the consequences. So
so then why did they get punished? אלא מאי טעמא איענוש? Ela
mai ta'ama i'anush? So why were they punished? So כדתניא, keditanya, like
we taught in the ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר אומר לא מתו בני
אהרן אלא על שהורו הלכה בפני משה רבן. Rebbe Eliezer omer, lo
meitu Bnei Aharon ela al she'horu halacha bifnei Moshe Rabban. No,
the problem was that they paskened in front of משה. Moshe. Nothing
to do with the קטורת, ketoret, nothing to do with being drunk,
that they paskened in front of משה. Moshe מאי דרש? Mai darash?
ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח. Venatnu Bnei Aharon Hakkohen esh
al hamizbe'ach. So it says that they should put fire. So they
gave the פסק psak that אף על פי שאש יורדת מן השמים
מצוה להביא מן ההדיוט. af al pi she'esh yoredes min hashamayim, mitzvah
lehavi min ha'hedyot.
You have to bring it from the הדיוט. hedyot. And therefore they
gave that פסק psak which is the right הלכה halacha that you
always add your own fire. And by the way they did it
בפני רבן. bifnei rabban. Now of course where were they told not
to do that or that you'd be חייב מיתה? chayiv misa? But
now we have completely certainly moved it into sort of the rabbinic
realm, you know, and areas that we're comfortable with. Now where do
they get that as of all things to say that that's what
was going on?
Because they didn't. They brought an אש. esh.
Exactly. Because not only that, it says ותצא אש vatetzei esh as
I just read you מלפני המזבח מלפני השם. milifnei HaMizbe'ach milifnei Hashem.
The אש esh came down. So there's אף על פי שאש יורדת
מן השמים. af al pi she'esh yoredes min hashamayim. The אש esh
was יורדת מן השמים yoredes min hashamayim right before they did their
act. And then it says they brought אש זרה אשר לא צוה
אותם. esh zara asher lo tziva osam. So even though it mentions
קטורת, ketoret, it also says אש זרה. esh zara. So you know,
that fire again not that the bringing of it was wrong, but
it was wrong that they did not sort of respect the proper
rabbinic authority, if you would, in the process of doing this. And
again talking about echoing the theme of the כהנים kohanim independent authority
from the rabbis. משה is of course the רבי, rabbi, משה רבינו,
Moshe Rabbeinu, and בני אהרן and they're sort of not you know
not going through the proper channels. I just want to show you
one minute that תוספות, Tosafos, a small תוספות Tosafos שהורו הלכה בפני
משה רבינו, she'horu halacha bifnei Moshe Rabbeinu, בתורת כהנים איכא פלוגתא דתנאי
טובא. betoras kohanim ika plugta detannayei tu. There's a lot of different
opinions of the תנאים tannaim why they died. מאי טעמא איענוש? Mai
ta'ama i'anush? איכא מאן דאמר מסיני נטלו. Ika man d'amar misinai natlu.
They finally got their payment from הר סיני Har Sinai because they
had you know saw God and did not and ויאכלו וישתו vayochlu
vayishtu behaved incorrectly, you know, that whole vision of God that the
זקנים zekenim had. ואית דאמרי מפני שאמרו מתי ימותו שני זקנים הללו
ואני ואתה ננהיג את הדור. Ve'is de'amri bifnei she'amru masai yamusu shnei
zekenim hallalu va'ani ve'ata nanhig es hador.
They were like every young generation impatient for the old generation to
die out. When will these two old guys die and we two
can take over? Again where they get that from the פסוקים psukim,
I don't know. ובפרק ארבע מיתות נמי מייתי לה. Uviferek Arba Misos
nami maisi lah. איכא מאן דאמר פרועי ראש היו. Ika man d'amar
parua rosh hayu. They went in with you know you know sort
of wild hair. Again where they get that from is not clear.
ואיכא מאן דאמר שתויי יין היו, Ve'ika man d'amar shtuyei yayin hayu,
which
there you understand the juxtaposition because right afterwards יין ושכר אל תשת.
yayin veshichar al tesht. ואיכא מאן דאמר מחוסרי בגדים היו. Ve'ika man
d'amar mechusarei begadim hayu. They weren't wearing all the other... so where
some of these are come from is not so clear, you can
look at the discussion over there, but there's a lot of speculation
in terms of trying to figure it out. רובי, Ruvi, had a
question? According to the פסוקים, psukim the אש esh killed them.
They were killed. They were zapped by fire. Right. ותצא אש Vatetzei
esh it says מלפני השם.
milifnei Hashem. The fire on the המזבח... Hamizbe'ach... right? ותצא אש... vatetzei
esh... Yeah, by ותצא אש. vatetzei esh. Yeah, but it doesn't say...
מלפני השם. milifnei Hashem.
Yeah, I think that's what the פסוק says. What? It could have
been from the... that's what the פסוקים psukim say. What do the
פסוקים say?
They don't say? ותצא אש... Vatetzei esh... is the question. מלפני
השם.
Milifnei
Hashem. I don't know where מלפני השם milifnei Hashem is anymore. Is
it from the עזרה, azarah, is it from the מזבח, mizbeach, is
it from the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right? There's a lot of
מלפני השם. milifnei Hashem. Yeah, just one more question then we have
to move on.
Even though obviously the פרשה parsha of אחרי מות starts that אחרי
מות שני בני אהרן, we're saying that this was already told to
them afterwards, even though Moshe was before the way?
Not necessarily that this פסוק, but the but that but that the
fact that it says אראה alludes to you that that part they
had known already ahead of time. You know, maybe not in this
פסוק, but that's I think how it's being read. Okay, let's keep
on going. Okay, now we move on to the walking backwards. יצא
ובא לו דרך כניסתו. Yatza uva lo derech kenisato. After he burns,
puts it on the fire, he now walks backwards. מנא הני מילי?
Mena hanei milei? So where do you know that you're supposed to
walk backwards when you leave the presence of God? אמר רב שמואל
בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן אמר קרא, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
amar Rabbi Yonatan amar kra, as the verse says, ויבא שלמה לבמה
אשר בגבעון ירושלים. Vayavo Shlomo labamah asher beGivon Yerushalayim.
Shlomo came to the altar in Gibeon, Jerusalem. That was where the
altar was prior to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. This was before
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was built. Altar to Gibeon, Jerusalem. Now
it should have said from Jerusalem. That's where he came from. But
it says גבעון ירושלים. Givon Yerushalayim. So וכי מה ענין
גבעון אצל ירושלים? Vekhi
mah inyan Givon etzel Yerushalayim? What does that mean Gibeon, Jerusalem? It's
like the same place, you know, that's the way it sounds. It
doesn't say he came from Jerusalem. אלא מקיש יציאתו מגבעון לירושלים לביאתו
מירושלים לגבעון. Ella makish yetziato miGivon liYerushalayim levi'ato miYerushalayim liGivon.
It connects the return trip. He's not just going from Jerusalem, he's
going to be returning also from Gibeon to Jerusalem. So by not
having the word from, it basically suggests both directions and it connects
leaving Gibeon and returning to Jerusalem to the going from Jerusalem to
Gibeon. מה ביאתו מירושלים לגבעון, Mah bi'ato miYerushalayim liGivon, the same way
when he came, פניו כלפי במה, panav klapei bamah, he obviously was
facing towards the במה. bamah. He was facing towards where he was
going. כדרך ביאתו, kederech bi'ato,
that's the way he was, obviously the way he was going, he
was facing that way. אף יציאתו מגבעון לירושלים, af yetziato miGivon liYerushalayim,
similarly when he returns, it's the same thing. פניו כלפי במה כדרך
ביאתו. panav klapei bamah kederech bi'ato. Yeah, so it means when he
begins the backwards journey at least, anyway, he continues to face the
במה bamah as he leaves. Okay. וכן, Vekhein, now
not only is this about the כהן גדול when he leaves the
קודש קדשים, we already spoke by the way about moving that intense
experience of the קודש קדשים on יום כפור Yom Kippur with קטורת
ketoret to making it a daily thing, you know, having an echo
of it on a daily basis of the burning of the קטורת.
ketoret. So now listen to this, the same idea about the exit.
That also is something that is experienced as a daily basis, this
way of exiting. וכן כהנים בעבודתם, Vekhein kohanim ba'avodatam, the כהנים kohanim
when they do their עבודה and they leave presumably the עזרה, azarah,
okay, ולויים בדוכנם, uleviyim beduchnam, and the לויים Levi'im are on the
דוכן, duchan, you know, doing their song,
which is also on the עזרה, azarah, in the עזרה, azarah, וישראל
במעמדם, veYisrael bema'amadam, and the ישראל, Yisrael, right, there would be representatives
of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael every day to stand over the daily
sacrifices to represent the people for whom those sacrifices are being brought,
and they would be in the עזרה. azarah. So now it's not
only when you leave the קודש קדשים and not only when you
leave the היכל, Heichal, even when you leave the עזרה, azarah, you
walk backwards. Okay? So now
partly it's learned from שלמה Shlomo maybe where it says במה. bamah.
So it's about the altar, even the presence of the altar you
walk backwards. Okay. כשהן נפטרים, Keshehen niftarim, when they leave, לא היו
מחזירים פניהם והולכים, lo hayu machzirim peneihem veholechim,
they would not turn their back, like turn their face around and
keep and have their back to the עזרה, azarah, אלא מצדדים פניהם
והולכים. ella metzadedim peneihem veholechim. They would
face towards the side. So maybe it wouldn't always be straight backwards
because you'd bump into people, but yeah, like maybe a little bit
like this, you know, or a little angle to the side, but
you would not have your back, certainly you would not have your
back towards the altar. Maybe that's also like a degree of difference.
Like when you leave the קודש קדשים, especially if you're the only
one around and you know, you walk and especially if you've got
curtains to guide you, you walk totally backwards. Okay? Whereas if in
this case a little less intense, you might angle yourself, but you're
still not turning your back.
What? Do people, you know, walk backwards when they leave a שול?
shul? Well, let's take a look. Okay. So again, what's fascinating here,
like the move of the קטורת ketoret to the daily קטורת, ketoret,
is the bringing of this as a more daily experience. And now
not only daily in the מקדש, Mikdash, let's look where the גמרא
Gemara goes now. וכן תלמיד הנפטר מרבו, Vekhein talmid haniftar merabbo, when
a student leaves his רבי, Rebbi, לא יחזיר, lo yachazir, right, it
says again this also this sort of מקדש Mikdash and תורה Torah
sort of, you know, dialectic or parallel. So we don't have a
מקדש Mikdash nowadays. What do we have? We have תורה. Torah. תורה
Torah is our cent... is our center. תורה Torah is our מקדש.
Mikdash. That's embodied in the רבי. Rebbi. So when you leave the
רבי, Rebbi, לא יחזיר פניו וילך, lo yachazir panav veyeilech, do not
turn your back and walk away, אלא מצדד פניו והולך, ella metzaded
panav veholech, you move to walk back, you know, towards, you know,
facing off to the side. כי הא, Ki ha, and now we'll
have a story, דרבי אלעזר, diRabbi Elazar, when רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
כד הוי מיפטר מיניה דרבי יוחנן, kad hava miptar minei deRabbi Yochanan,
he was a student of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, when he would
take his leave of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So it depends who
would have who was leaving, okay. כד הוי בעי רבי יוחנן למיזל,
Kad hava ba'ei Rabbi Yochanan lemizal, if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was
the one who wanted to walk away... הוה גחין קאי ר' אלעזר
אדוכתיה, havei gachin kai Rebbi Elazar aduchtaih, ר' אלעזר Rebbi Elazar would
prostrate himself and stay in his place עד דהוה מיכסי רבי יוחנן
מיניה, ad d'havei michsi Rebbi Yochanan mineih, until ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
was no longer visible to him. So if the rebbe is leaving,
you prostrate yourself and the rebbe takes his leave and then you
get up and you leave. וכד הוה בעי ר' אלעזר למיפטרא, v'chad
havei ba'ei Rebbi Elazar l'meipt'ra, and if ר' אלעזר Rebbi Elazar had
to take his leave, הוה קאזיל לאחוריה, havei ka'azil l'achoreih, he would
walk backwards עד דמיכסי מיניה דר' יוחנן, ad d'michsi minei d'Rebbi Yochanan,
and he would walk backwards until he was no longer visible by
ר' יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, meaning he would walk backwards until ר' יוחנן,
Rebbi Yochanan, meaning, you know why?
Since ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan couldn't see him, him turning his back
would not be disrespectful. Okay, so he would wait until he could
no longer be seen by ר' יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. But you see
now this, the embodying of this on a daily basis and in
the context of תורה, Torah, not just of מקדש. Mikdash. Similarly, רבא,
Rava, כד הוה מיפטר מיניה דרב יוסף, kad havei mip'tar mineih d'Rav
Yosef, when רבא Rava would take his leave of רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, הוה אזיל לאחוריה, havei azil l'achoreih, he would walk backwards, רבא,
Rava, and now we start to see the problem of walking backwards
without having a side view mirror, עד דמנפדן כרעי, ad d'minadp'in karaei,
until his legs would get, would bang against things because he's walking
backwards, ומתפיין אסקופתא דבי רב יוסף דמא, u'mitpayan askofta d'vei Rav Yosef
dama, and the doorposts of רב יוסף Rav Yosef would get
dirty with blood. So he'd walk out of the house, out through
the doorway backward and his legs would bang against the doorway which
maybe had splinters and they would, and it would, and you know,
get blood on the doorway. Quite also invoking the whole קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach image, right? The blood on the doorway. Alright, so anyway,
so that's what he would do. So אמר, amar, maybe not intentionally,
but he was willing to allow for that risk. אמרו
ליה לרב יוסף, amru leih l'Rav Yosef, הכי עביד רבא, hachi avid
Rava, so people told רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, you should know that
this is what רבא's Rava doing when he takes his leave of
you. Why did they have to tell him? He was blind, he
didn't know. So they informed him, you know, you didn't know, I
want you to know what happens when רבא Rava takes leave. Even
though you can't see him, and this is interesting, and maybe even
in contrast to the previous discussion which is once ר' יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan couldn't see ר' אלעזר, Rebbi Elazar, ר' אלעזר Rebbi Elazar felt
free to turn his back. Even though רב יוסף Rav Yosef couldn't
see רבא, Rava, maybe other people could see, you know, and therefore
but it would still be disrespectful in his presence even if he
couldn't see to turn his back. So he told, so רבא, Rava,
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said to him, יהא רעוא דתירם רישך
אכולא כרכא, yehei ra'ava d'tairem reishach a'kula karcha, may it be God's
will that your head, you know, your head
should be lifted over over the entire city, which רש"י Rashi says
means like you should be a ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. המהרש"א Hamaharsha
says it means basically you should be the head of both ישיבות,
Yeshivot, not just, you know, the one, you and אביי have competing
ישיבות. Yeshivot. So anyway, he was very impressed with that. Okay, אמר
ר' אלכסנדרי, amar Rebbi Alexandri, he didn't stop. He didn't stop. אמר
ר' אלכסנדרי, amar Rebbi Alexandri, let's read a little bit more, אמר
ר' יהושע בן לוי, amar Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi, המתפלל צריך שיפסיע
שלוש פסיעות לאחוריו, hamitpalel tzarich sheyafsi'a shalosh pesiot l'achorav,
and now we also get a translation in תפילה, tefillah, another encounter
of God. There's מקדש, Mikdash, there's תורה, Torah, there's תפילה, tefillah, right?
And in תפילה tefillah you're in God's presence so you walk backwards,
three steps backwards, ואחר כך יתן שלום, v'achar kach yiten shalom, and
then you say, you know, as in עושה שלום במרומיו הוא יעשה
שלום,
oseh
shalom bimromav
hu ya'aseh shalom, but you say goodbye first, you walk back, it's
interesting, don't say goodbye and then walk back, first walk back and
then say goodbye. I'm trying to think of the significance of the
difference of like, you know,
I mean I guess because once you said goodbye you're seeing yourself
as no longer in the presence. So you first want to sort
of demonstrate a certain distancing of the presence, you know, and then
say goodbye.
But you also don't want to say goodbye, right?
Oh, the reluctance to say goodbye, that could be.
But in our formulation it's not really say goodbye, it's יתן שלום,
yiten shalom, it's the gift of עושה שלום.
oseh shalom. It's a ceremony. Right. So why is it the ceremony,
but why does it end the ceremony rather than before? Yeah, the
גמרא, Gemara, I'm just somehow there seems a significance, first you do
the steps, then you say עושה שלום. oseh shalom. But again, you
know, but yeah, I mean you sort of first have to break
off, right, you have to break off the intense connection and step
back and then you sort of sum it up with the עושה
שלום.
oseh shalom.
This is our model of after יום כיפור Yom Kippur as what
we're saying.
Yeah, that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Okay, so, what? You
show your respect before you ask for the ברכה. bracha.
Right,
oh, that's true. Saying שלום shalom is a request for a ברכה,
bracha, although the whole שמונה עשרה's Shemoneh Esrei been a request for
a ברכה, bracha, but yes. Okay. אמר ליה רב מרדכי, amar leih
Rav Mordechai, so רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai says, כיון שפסע שלוש פסיעות
לאחוריו התם מיבעי ליה למיקם, kivan shepasa shalosh pesiot l'achorav hatam miba'ei
leih l'meikam,
once you take your three steps back you gotta stand there, meaning
don't immediately go back to where you were, wait there for a
moment. משל לתלמיד הנפטר מרבו, mashal l'talmid haniftar merabo, it's interesting how
we now look at leaving God's presence in שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei,
we're going to go back to the previous model of leaving your
rebbe. So when a student leaves his rebbe, אם חוזר לאלתר, im
chozer l'altar, if he steps away from his rebbe and then immediately
walks back, דומה לכלב ששב על קיאו, domeh l'kelev sheshav al ke'o,
it's like a dog returning to his vomit. Now I have to
tell you, I never understood this. Who would want to make an
analogy with God or the rebbe being vomit, you know? So I,
I really don't, I mean somebody's got to explain to me the
metaphor in the image. But somehow it's not respectful to show you
take your leave. You take your leave means, you know, that that
place is where the רבי rebbe is, where God is. I've, you
know, I've stepped back and now I have to like honor that
place, you know, I don't just to walk back shows I don't
respect, you know, the presence of God or the presence of my
רבי.
rebbe. So חוזר לאלתר, chozer l'altar, what's the main point? In other
words, if he just walks away immediately?
No, חוזר chozer at least as understood to me means you just
leave, but it means that and but the כלב ששב על קיאו
kelev she-shav al ke'o means you go back. You take your steps
back, you finish שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and then you walk right
back to where you were standing. And that happens a lot, by
the way. Here you are, you're standing שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei by
the table, right, you walk back, you're done, and then okay, I'm
going back to the table where I was sitting. So you actually
say no, no, no, you have to like wait here a few
steps.
For how long?
Just say, yeah, I think they say... well, whatever, you know, I
think the הילוך ד' אמות, hiluch daled amot, but I don't understand
the image of כלב ששב על קיאו, kelev she-shav al ke'o, I
must say. But the קיא ki is you debase yourself.
You debase yourself?
To honor the רבי. rebbe. Right, but I'm right, so I do
understand that it is debasing, I don't understand like what is the
קיא? ke'o?
Your own קיא, ke'o, you're your own. You're going back to your,
you're reversing your debasement, you know. Oh!
Oh, you're saying the process, you're saying the process of stepping back
is basically like I'm...
No, but what
Dov is saying is like it's a type of אנכי עפר ואפר,
anochi afar va'efer, like you know, I, right? Is that what you
mean? Like you're I'm nothing and I'm and I, you know, and
I therefore I'm so little, you know, and therefore you leave so
you've demonstrated your lowliness and then you're reentering the space. That's interesting.
That's interesting. Okay, we have to end here, we're already a little
bit over, we will continue with the whole stepping back choreography tomorrow.